Register of the Latvian Oral History Project interviews
Hoover Institution Archives
Latvian Oral History Project interviews
1995-2016
99028
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 20 digital sound files (0.8 linear feet, 1.71 GB)
Sound recordings of interviews of Latvian political leaders, governmental officials, and others relating to political, social, and economic conditions in Latvia. Includes transcripts of questions and some related printed matter. Project sponsored by the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace. Interviews conducted by David Jacobs. Digital copies also available.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of some sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to other sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1999, with an increment acquired in 2016.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The initial set of interviews were conducted in 1999 and 2000 by David Jacobs of the Hoover Institution Archives in an attempt to document political and social conditions, as well as cultural trends, in Latvia at the time. Each interviewee was asked a set of prepared questions designed to elicit information on leading issues of the day in a country that had become independent again in 1991, following the break-up of the Soviet Union. Topics covered in the interviews include Latvia's relations with the Russian Federation, its efforts to join the European Union (a goal that Latvia achieved in 2004), and the status of the sizeable Russian minority in the country. The role of business interests in Latvian politics was also addressed in a number of the interviews, as were questions of regional and social inequalities in the country. The interviews were recorded on compact sound cassettes and have since been digitized so that researchers can listen to them.
The sizeable increment to the collection is comprised of interviews conducted in 2016 (again by David Jacobs) with Latvian government officials, politicians, historians, and archivists. Each interviewee was asked a set of questions tailored to his or her position, as well as a set of questions that was asked of each individual. The questions focus on the 25th anniversary of renewed independence for Latvia: each interviewee was asked to give an account of the country's successes and failures since 1991. Issues such as NATO and European Union membership are addressed in most of the interviews, as are relations between Latvia and the Russian Federation. Other topics include the demographic situation in Latvia following the Great Recession, when some 400,000 Latvians left the country in search of employment. It should be noted that some of the interviews consist of informal discussions rather than structured question and answer sessions.
The increment also contains background information, as well as lists of the questions that each interviewee was asked. There is also a considerable amount of printed matter, consisting largely of brochures and handouts provided by some of the interviewees.
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace.; Jacobs, David.; Latvia--Economic conditions--1991-; Latvia--Politics and government--1991-; Latvia--Social conditions.; Audiotapes.
- Sound recordings of interviews, 1999-2000; 21.0 sound cassettes (Box 1)
  - Cimdars, Arnis, 1999 March 3
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006427
    Scope and Contents note
    Elga Zalite interviews Cimdars, chairman of the Central Election Committee, in Riga, Latvia.
  - Panelejevs, Andrejs, 1999 March 15
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006428
    Chairman of the party Latvijas Cels ("Latvia's Way").
  - Elerte, Sarmite, 1999 March 17
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006429
    Editor of Diena.
  - Johnson, Steven C., 1999 March 31
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006430
    Editor of The Baltic Times.
  - Felsbergs, Valdis, 1999 April 12
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006431
    Co-chairman of the Latvian Green Party.
  - Bojars, Juris, 1999 April 19
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006432
    Chairman of the Latvian Social Democratic Association.
  - Lase, Ieva, 1999 April 28 - May 5
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006433
    Member of "The French Group," an informal circle of Latvian intellectuals deported to the Gulag in the early 1950s for reading and discussing banned literature, including the works of French existentialist philosophers.
  - Skele, Andris, 1999 May 20
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006434
    Leader of the People's Party (Tautas Partija).
  - Makarovs, Vladimirs, 1999 May 21
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006435
    Minister of social welfare.
  - Krupenkovs, Imants, 1999 May 26
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006436
    Employee, Latvian Ministry of Economics.
  - Jurkans, Janis, 1999 June 2
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006437
    Leader of the National Harmony Party and former foreign minister of Latvia.
  - Kaupers, Renars, 1999 June 8
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006438
    Leader of Prata Vetra (Brainstorm), the most popular Latvian rock group.
  - Muiznieks, Nils, 1999 June 9
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006439
    Employee, Soros Fund of Latvia.
  - Kalnins, Imants, 1999 June 11
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006440
    Composer and member of Parliament.
  - Tjarve, Rolands, 1999 June 17
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006441
    General director of Latvian Television, the state broadcasting company.
  - Druviete, Ina, 1999 June 30
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006442
    Linguist.
  - Straume, Janis, 1999 July 1
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006443
    Speaker of the Saiema (Latvian Parliament). This interview was conducted through an interpreter; it is in Latvian and English.
  - Petersone, Valda, 1999 July 9
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006444
    Deputy director of the state archives of Latvia.
  - Birkavs, Valdis, 1999 July 22
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006445
    Latvian foreign minister from 1994 to 1999.
  - Ulmanis, Guntis and Nils Muiznieks, 2000 October 25
    Use copy reference number: 99028_a_0006446
    In separate sessions, Jacobs interviews Ulmanis, former state president, and Muiznieks. The Ulmanis interview was assisted by a translator.
- Interviewee questions, circa 1999 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Also includes article about Imants Kalnins.
- Printed matter, 1995-1999
  - Article, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Brochures and pamphlets, 1997-1998, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Clippings (photocopies), 1999 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Newsletters, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- 2016 Increment, 2009-2016 (Digital sound files, Box 2)
  - Digital sound files of interviews, 2016 (Reading room workstation)
    Twenty digital .mp3 sound files (1.71 GB).
    - Zālite, Elga, 2016 September 4; 3.0 digital files
      Latvian historian.
    - Zeltīts, Raivis, 2016 September 20; 1.0 digital file
      Latvian politician and general secretary of the National Alliance party.
    - Spolītis, Veiko, 2016 September 20; 1.0 digital file
      Member of the Saiema (Latvian Parliament).
    - Pildegovičs, Andrejs, 2016 September 21; 1.0 digital file
      State Secretary, Latvian Foreign Ministry.
    - Ušakovs, Nils, 2016 September 21; 1.0 digital file
      Mayor of Riga and head of the Concord Party.
    - Rozenberga, Aiva, 2016 September 21; 1.0 digital file
      Head of the Latvian Institute.
    - Kalniņa, Inese, 2016 September 22; 1.0 digital file
      Head of the Latvian State Archives.
    - Kalniņš, Ojārs, 2016 September 23; 1.0 digital file
      Chairman of the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the Saiema (Latvian Parliament).
    - Lehris, Ainars and Jonathan B. (Al-Jazeera reporter), 2016 September 23; 1.0 digital file
      Latvian historian. Conversation recorded in a café with ambient noise.
    - Razāns, Andris, 2016 September 26; 1.0 digital file
      Former Latvian ambassador to the United States.
    - Slaidiņa, Inguna, 2016 September 27; 1.0 digital file
      Deputy Director of the Latvian Archives.
    - Jakovļeva, Mārīte; Margarita Barzdeviča; and Elga Zālite, 2016 September 27; 1.0 digital file
      Latvian historians.
    - Merivoo-Parro, Maarja, 2016 September 27; 1.0 digital file
      Estonian historian.
    - Lehris, Ainārs and Maarja Merivoo-Parro, 2016 September 27; 1.0 digital file
      Latvian and Estonian historians.
    - Ščerbinskis, Valters, 2016 September 28; 2.0 digital files
    - Jēkabsons, Ēriks, 2016 September 28; 1.0 digital file
    - Spirğe, Alda, 2016 September; 1.0 digital file
      Vice principal and English teacher at Jelgavas Gymnasium (part 1 of interview is missing due to technical failure).
  - Interviewee materials, 2014-2016
    Contains background materials on those interviewed and lists of questions asked.
    - Zālite, Elga, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Zeltīts, Raivis, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Pildegovičs, Andrejs, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Spolītis, Veiko, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Ušakovs, Nils, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Rozenberga, Aiva, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Kalniņa, Inese, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Kalniņs, Ojārs, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Lehris, Ainārs, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Razāns, Andris, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - Slaidiņa, Inguna, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - Barzdeviča, Margarita, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - Jakovļeva, Mārīte, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - Merivoo-Parro, Maarja, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    - Ščerbinskis, Valters, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - Jēkabsons, Ēriks, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - Spirğe, Alda, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Printed matter, 2009-2016
    - Brochures and handouts, 2013-2015, undated
      - General, various Latvian museums, undated (Box-folder 2: 18)
      - Latvijas Institūt, 2013-2015 (Box-folder 2: 19-20)
      - Latvijas Nacionālā bibliotēka, undated (Box-folder 2: 21)
      - Lestene memorial, undated (Box-folder 2: 22)
      - Likteņdārzs memorial, undated (Box-folder 2: 23)
    - Monographs, 2013-2016
      - Zelta ābele, 1993-2013, 2014 (Box-folder 2: 24)
      - Zelta ābele, 2012, 2013, 2015, 2013-2016 (Box-folder 2: 25)
    - Serial issues, 2009, 2016
      - Jelgavas Vēstnesis, 2016 (Box-folder 2: 32)
      - Plēsums, 2009 (Box-folder 2: 27)
      - Trimdas arhīvi atgriežas. 4. daļa, 2009 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Video disc, Latvian Nationwide Song and Dance Celebration, Latvijas Institūt, 2013 (Box-folder 2: 29)